<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A disswasive from contention being a sermon preached and designed for the last itineration of the King's preachers in the county Palatine of Lancaster / by Zachary Taylor ...</title>
            <author>Taylor, Zachary, 1653-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R81</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12073922</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12073922</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53540</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53540)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 829:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A disswasive from contention being a sermon preached and designed for the last itineration of the King's preachers in the county Palatine of Lancaster / by Zachary Taylor ...</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Zachary, 1653-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Gain for William Cadman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XVII, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53540:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53540:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISSVVASIVE FROM Contention. BEING A SERMON Preached and Deſigned for the laſt <hi>Itineration</hi> of the King's <hi>Preachers</hi> in the County <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> By <hi>Zachary Taylor.</hi> A. M. <hi>Vicar</hi> of <hi>Ormskirk,</hi> and one of the King's <hi>Preachers</hi> in that County.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>St. James</hi> ch. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>14.16.</hi>
               </bibl> If you have bitter Zeal, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and Strife in your Hearts, glory not, and lye not againſt the Truth. For where Zeal (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and Strife is, there is Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and every Evil Work.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Gain,</hi> for <hi>William Cadman,</hi> at the <hi>Pope's Head</hi> in the <hi>New-Exchange,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53540:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53540:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Lawrence,</hi> Earl of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi> Sir <hi>John Ernle,</hi> Chancellour, and Under Treaſurer of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer.</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Dearing. Sidney Godolphin,</hi> Eſq; Sir <hi>Stephen Fox.</hi> The Lords, Commiſſioners of his Majeſty's <hi>Treaſury.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is an <hi>Aſperſion</hi> caſt peculiarly on our <hi>County,</hi> by a <hi>Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes</hi> of the <hi>Faction, That the Growth of</hi> Popery <hi>among us, is for want of an able</hi> Miniſtry <hi>to Inſtruct and Settle the People.</hi> A Suggeſtion, truly <hi>Fanatical,</hi> (i.e.) it wants both <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi> The firſt: for who learnt the <hi>Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> to blemiſh the Reputation of Perſons, whoſe <hi>Abilities</hi> he is altogether unacquainted with. And for the <hi>latter,</hi> there hath more <hi>Converts</hi> been gained to the <hi>Church,</hi> within theſe laſt five Years, than the Key for <hi>Catholicks</hi> hath opened the Heart of. But the <hi>Sollicitations</hi> which your <hi>Honour,</hi> we hope, will favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably admit, in behalf of ſome Convict <hi>Recuſants,</hi> who having Legally joyned our <hi>Communion,</hi> labour to be diſcharged from the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> will be a more ample Confutation of ſo Infamous a <hi>Scandal,</hi> than any thing I can expect to Offer.</p>
            <p>And for this my preſent Eſſay, I foreſee it will be conſtrued ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an incouraging, than weakening of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> For though there would be no ſuch Fatal Stroak unto the <hi>Tripple Crown,</hi> as our uniting in the Bond of Peace; which is my Prayer as well as Province. Yet, when ever we deſign to reduce theſe <hi>wandring Sheep</hi> unto their Folds, they exclaim, as if we were giving Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence for Beaſts of Prey to Forage. Reputing it the <hi>Property</hi> of a good <hi>Shepherd,</hi> to be always in purſuit of <hi>Wolves,</hi> not conſidering, that in his abſence the <hi>ninety nine</hi> may go aſtray, and periſh in the Wilderneſs.</p>
            <p>And never more need to project this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, than at this Seaſon, when the <hi>Sheep</hi> have exchang'd with the <hi>Wolf,</hi> their Cloathing, for his <hi>Ravenage,</hi> and we are expos'd to as much danger from the <hi>Sword</hi> of the Lord, in the hand of the <hi>Saints,</hi> as that of <hi>Peter</hi>'s in his degenerated Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>The juſt <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of theſe Fears (which by Vertue of my Cure, I take my ſelf obliged as much to obviate, as any other) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:53540:3"/>with a proſpect of that Advantage which their <hi>Adherene</hi> would afford againſt the Common Enemy, gave Being to this <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive from Contention.</hi> Which I intreat the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who ſhall be pleaſed to read it, to peruſe with ſomething more <hi>Coolneſs,</hi> than their Brethren <hi>Auditors</hi> who heard it. For the <hi>Calumnies</hi> they ſpread, and the Miſchief they deſigned me for it (as if they meant to let us underſtand, they were ſo little Edifyed by our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptions, that, <hi>If the</hi> Righteous <hi>ſhould ſmite them, they would not take it for a</hi> Kindneſs, <hi>nor allow of his</hi> Reproof <hi>to be</hi> healing, <hi>as an</hi> excellent Oyl; <hi>but the rather</hi> grievous, <hi>as what doth</hi> break <hi>their Head.</hi> This conſtrained me in my own Vindication, as well as for the Benefit of others; who by their ſupercilious Cenſures, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged in their Opinions about it, and by that means prevented from the hearing of it, to ſend theſe Papers on the <hi>Itineration,</hi> in the Room of their Maſter. And I humbly beſeech your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> to favour it with a <hi>Protection;</hi> for then, though it may chance to feel, it will not fear their <hi>Obloquies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Duty, no leſs than Prudence, was I bound to ſeek a <hi>Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> under the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage of your Honour, from whoſe Influence theſe our Labours are quickened, and our Induſtry animated. For we du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly value our ſelves as thoſe happy Instances, by the Countenancing of whom, your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> do reſolve to convince the <hi>World,</hi> how falſly and unjustly our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> Propheſy of the Regreſs of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>Lords,</hi> this <hi>Provident Eſtabliſhment,</hi> of which, your <hi>Honours</hi> be the <hi>Guardians,</hi> founded by the late Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of happy Memory, is the only <hi>Relique</hi> of that mature Deliberation, which by our firct <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> was found the best Expedient to propagate the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> I mean, the Commanding their Majesties <hi>Chaplains</hi> to Itinerate the Kingdom, and in their reſpective Diviſions, to Preach the <hi>Reformation.</hi> Which, how ſucceſsful it was, the Event demonstrated.</p>
            <p>Though we confeſs our ſelves much their <hi>Inferiours</hi> for Ability, we are unwilling, to be thought behind them in our Duty. And therefore, in all due Gratitude acknowledge your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Generous Candor on ſo Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable a Settlement, and ſo good a Work: Whom to Revere as our <hi>Patrons,</hi> is the Ambition of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt Humble</hi> Client, <hi>and obſequious Servant</hi> Zachary Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53540:3"/>
            <head>A Diſſwaſive FROM <hi>Contention, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. 17. V. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The beginning of Strife is as when one letteth out Water: therefore leave off Contention before it be meddled with.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT there are <hi>Diviſions</hi> among us needs our <hi>Lamentation</hi> more than <hi>Proof:</hi> and a <hi>Rupture</hi> ſo viſible, requires a <hi>Healing Hand,</hi> more than a <hi>Weeping Eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Deſign therefore is, to invite all thoſe, that are the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> to <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> by expoſing the Dreadful Conſequences of <hi>Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities</hi> and <hi>Diviſions:</hi> and by admoniſhing them of ſome <hi>Waſting Impieties,</hi> which are the Inſeparable <hi>Adjuncts</hi> of their <hi>Separation.</hi> For when they apprehend the <hi>Guilt,</hi> we
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53540:4"/>may hope they will be wiſe enough to avoid the <hi>Danger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour gives us this <hi>Characteriſtick</hi> to diſtinguiſh of <hi>Falſe Prophets; You ſhall know them by their Fruits,</hi> Mat. 7.16. <hi>i. e.</hi> by ſuch Emergencies as are the natural Effects of their Principles, or unreproved Practices. The common Effects, I ſay, for I acknowledge it (and I wiſh our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren would do ſo to) an injuſtice to charge Impiety up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Party, which neither favour it by their Poſitions, nor connive at it in the Execution. But where the <hi>Fruit is Evil, the Tree muſt be Corrupt,</hi> Mat. 12.33. And what the Guilt of our Diſſentions are, unto that Faction that foment them, will appear in the Diſcuſſing of this <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme. The beginning of ſtrife,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Words are a Diſſwaſive from <hi>Diſſention,</hi> and by repreſenting the Original, Progreſs and Effect thereof, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe us to leave off <hi>Contention</hi> before it grow <hi>Tumultuous,</hi> which is the Importance of our <hi>Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>In</hi> Hithp. <hi>antequam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſceatſe.</hi> Jun. &amp; Trem.</note> Before it be meddled with;</hi> For it is not properly <hi>Contention,</hi> till the adverſe Party meddels or joyneth Iſſue, till there be, what the <hi>Original</hi> implies, <hi>A reciprocation of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel;</hi> that it <hi>Ferment</hi> and grow <hi>Impetuous.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Tho the <hi>Original</hi> be, <hi>But as the letting out of Water,</hi> which in it ſelf is a ſmall and trivial thing, and may be done by Unwarineſs and Imprudence; yet in the cloſe, it may become no leſs pernitious, than if it were willful and adviſed; For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Progreſs, paſſage being made, it ſpreads alike; The Sluce cut, or the Flood gates drawn, on what occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoever, gives equal Liberty to the Violence of the <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent;</hi> which,</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the Event is fatal, may overflow, and Deluge the Country; and ſo <hi>Theodotion</hi> renders it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The beginning of Strife is an Inundation of Waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not inſiſt upon the Propriety of the Holy Spirits reſembling <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Parties</hi> unto a <hi>Confluence of Waters;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53540:4"/>nor the <hi>Madneſs</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> to the <hi>Raging</hi> of the <hi>Sea. Pſal.</hi> 89.9. but apply my ſelf,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To enquire into the <hi>Original</hi> of our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> which being like the <hi>Letting out of Water,</hi> a trival, and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Action (for I would have the Charity to believe, that our <hi>Difference</hi> was no deſign of Malice) implies the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be light and ſmall of little moment, or importance. And ſo indeed it is.
<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terum horum.</note> We are agreed as to the <hi>Subſtance of Religion,</hi> and our Brethren Glory,
<note place="margin">Adam on the Short Cat.</note> that they can prove their <hi>Doctrine by the Authority of our Articles and Homilies.</hi> They come nearer yet; and acknowledge, <hi>That they may Communicate with our Churches,
<note place="margin">Mr. Nye.</note> without ſin;</hi> and as God ſaid of his People ſo we, <hi>Oh that there was ſuch an heart in them!</hi> Deut. 5.29. Indeed occaſionally they can joyn our Communion, but is not this an evidence againſt them; or doth not the Peace of Chriſt's Church oblige us conſtantly to adhere, to what occaſionaly we can comply with.</p>
            <p>Whence then come our Diviſions. <hi>Dear my God!</hi> that Chriſt body ſhould be rent and torn upon ſuch poore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. The Quarrel is <hi>De lana Caprina,</hi> even in the literal ſenſe about <hi>Habits</hi> and <hi>Veſtments,</hi> Whether a <hi>Cloke</hi> be not more Decent in the worſhip of God then a <hi>Gown,</hi> or <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice.?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether it be not greater ſcandal to <hi>kneel</hi> at the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> then <hi>ſit,</hi> or <hi>lean</hi> as doth their <hi>Head</hi> the <hi>Pope?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Set Forms of Prayer</hi> compoſed to the mind of <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> have not as fair a Claim unto the <hi>Spirit</hi> as unpremeditated <hi>Extemporary Effuſions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether a <hi>Liturgy</hi> in which the People bear a part (whence it is call'd the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> being <hi>performed</hi> in <hi>Common,</hi> by the <hi>Flock,</hi> and <hi>Paſtor</hi>) be not a <hi>Worſhip,</hi> full
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53540:5"/>as Edifying, as that which may betray men to the ſurrep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Wandring thoughts, having no Office to recall their Roving mind, but what concludes the laſt, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether it be a <hi>Super-erogation</hi> of <hi>Devotion,</hi> to ſet apart and conſecrate ſome <hi>Common Dayes</hi> to the Worſhip of God, in which we may <hi>Commemorate</hi> what was therin tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the more <hi>Eminent inſtances</hi> of the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>Religious Education</hi> of <hi>Infants,</hi> may not be prudently ſecured, by requiring Parents to provide <hi>Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors;</hi> either to <hi>Rebuke their negligence,</hi> if themſelves ſhould be ſlack, or <hi>ſupply their Office,</hi> becauſe they are Mortal?</p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Confirmation,</hi> the <hi>Laying on of Hands,</hi> or the <hi>Bleſſing of the Biſhop,</hi> upon the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of a <hi>Novices Faith,</hi> be not an <hi>Advantagious Expedient</hi> for the <hi>Grounding Youth,</hi> in the <hi>Princeples</hi> of the <hi>True Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>Signing Infants</hi> with the <hi>Croſs</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> can make us more <hi>Superſtitious</hi> than others, whoſe <hi>Averſion</hi> looks, as tho they were <hi>aſhamed</hi> of the <hi>Croſs of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, Whether the <hi>Communicating</hi> with the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians,</hi> in ſuch <hi>Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> as they duly practiſed before the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> uſurped upon the <hi>Weſtern Church:</hi> can be a <hi>Symbolizing</hi> with the preſent <hi>Papacy? Or</hi> if you pleaſe,</p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>abuſe</hi> of things in themſelves moſt <hi>Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant,</hi> be a ſufficient reaſon to <hi>reject</hi> their <hi>Uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and ſuch as theſe are the things, which make men ſhun our Communion, Flock into Conventicles, and Divide into Factions. Theſe were the beginings of that Breach, now grown into an open, and a dreadful Schiſm. And is the Peace of Chriſt Church ſo meer a Cypher that men may be excuſed, who are leſs tender of it, then tenacious of their own Opinions. One of the laſt Legacies that Chriſt bequeathed unto his Church was <hi>Peace, my Peace I leave with you, my Peace I give unto you</hi> Joh. 14.27.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53540:5"/>One of the laſt Prayers, that he offered to his Father was for <hi>Unity, Holy Father keep them, That they may be one as we are one,</hi> Joh. 11. The firſt deſcriptcion, that you meet with of the Church; is taken from her <hi>Uniformity,</hi> and her Diſciples <hi>Unaminity</hi> Act. 2.42. <hi>&amp;</hi> c. 4.32. Such Inclinations hath the Religion, Chriſt came to ſettle unto <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> that it is moſt Emphatically ſtiled, <hi>The Goſpel of Peace;</hi> Ephe. 6.16. The Title that he bears, is, <hi>The Prince of Peace,</hi> Iſai. 9.6. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty we Worſhip is the <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.2. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.20. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 33.7.</note> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Peace. Diſciples,</hi> the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Peace. Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> the <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> the <hi>Counſellors</hi> of <hi>Peace.</hi> In a word, ſo important, this Duty, that God doth ſeem, as if he need to promiſe to his Church no more, than to make her <hi>Officers Peace,</hi> Iſai. 60.17. Nor did the Apoſtles know to pray for more, then the <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> ſo large a Bleſsing, that it doth <hi>paſs all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> Phil. 4.7. And can there be a <hi>Zealot</hi> that would unravel all this, fruſtrate <hi>God's Promiſe,</hi> and diſpence with this <hi>Chriſtian Duty;</hi> for the Sake of a few <hi>Rites,</hi> and little <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> I am ſorry, that we have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to lament there ſhould be ſuch: But rather, then reflect on their <hi>Infirmity;</hi> I ſhall intreat their Devotion, to joyn with us, in <hi>Praying for the Peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> Pſal. 122.6. For alas! though we have diſcourſt it long enough; we have had no better Succeſs, then what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> complaines off; <hi>For when we laboured for Peace, and ſpoke unto them thereof, they made themſelves ready for Battle,</hi> Pſal. 120.7. which, how they have promoted comes to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered under.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Progreſs of theſe <hi>Diviſions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quae veris addere falſa gandet, et é minimo ſua per Veſtigia creſcit.</note> which <hi>Spread like Water,</hi> ſpeedily, and dangerouſly. What that may be, the common Noiſe will tell you, that gives falſe Rumors,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53540:6"/>Wings, to fly abroad, and ſpread her Poiſon.</p>
            <p>I know, I ſhall incur the Cenſure of a <hi>Diſcontented Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> For ſome there be, whoſe Actions are ſo bad; that <hi>Truth</hi> is a <hi>Scandal;</hi> and the Relation no better than a <hi>Libel.</hi> All the Favour that I expect, is this: That where their Conſcience tells them, that I ſpeak the <hi>Truth;</hi> they would receive the Admonition peacably, and conſider it ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly: and to requite this Candor, if in any thing, I chance to miſtake them; I do promiſe to make them Satisfaction, as publick as the Injury. And on the Hopes of their Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, either admitting the <hi>Truth,</hi> or informing my <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;</hi> I take the Freedom to tell them, that <hi>Miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>Miſtakes, Falſities,</hi> and <hi>Fictions</hi> were the <hi>Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of theſe <hi>Diviſions.</hi> for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They ſeek to juſtify their <hi>Non-conformity</hi> by venting Falſe; at leaſt, dubious, and unſound Poſitions. Such are theſe,</p>
            <p>That our <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are <hi>Parts</hi> of <hi>Divine Worſhip.</hi> But where do they find this, or do we teach any ſuch thing? No ſurely; for are <hi>Parts of Divine Worſhip</hi> alterable accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the difference of Time, and Place?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Art: of the Church of England,</hi> 24.</note> May they be ordained, chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or aboliſhed by Authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, as we aſſert of theſe. They might be aſhamed of ſuch a <hi>Calumny:</hi> And I deſire, they would adviſe with <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> of their own Denomination,
<note place="margin">Latae á Deo Ceremoniae ſunt Cultus Dei: ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus inſtitutae non ſunt Cultus Dei; ſed ſi bonae ſunt, cultui divino ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viunt. <hi>Vrſ. Cat. par.</hi> 3: <hi>Q.</hi> 92. Ab Eccleſia Inſtitutae Ceremoniae non ſunt Cultus Dei. 16. <hi>Q</hi> 103.</note> and theſe will tell them, <hi>That Ceremonies which God eſtabliſheth, are indeed the Worſhip of God; but what men inſtitute, are not the Worſhip of God. Though if they be good, they are Subſerviceable to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</hi> And again, <hi>Ceremontes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the Church, are not the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</hi> And I wiſh this may ſatisfy them.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53540:6"/>
            <p>But they pretend the ſame Reaſon to ſeparate from us, that we had to forſake the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> How implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is Malice! Were bare Ceremonies the cauſe of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion? or what do you mean by theſe Notorious Falſities? Do we frame <hi>New Articles of Faith,</hi> or equallize <hi>Tradition</hi> unto <hi>Scripture?</hi> Do we ſubject the <hi>Scepter</hi> to the <hi>Croſier,</hi> or arrogate <hi>Infallibility</hi> unto our Church? Do we offer Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the <hi>Quick</hi> and <hi>Dead?</hi> or do <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> and he like, come out off our <hi>Mint?</hi> Or do you meet any of our Church, that will juſtifie <hi>Rome,</hi> as you do us; and confeſs, that ſhe is ſound in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Morra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> So groſs the Untruth, ſo apparent the Envy; that I admire that any one, can have, either ſo great Impudence, for to averr it, or ſo little Senſe to be deceived by it.</p>
            <p>Yet, the <hi>Impoſers</hi> you will ſay were <hi>Culpable,</hi> and the <hi>Guilt,</hi> if there be any, <hi>lies at their Door.</hi> By the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Malefactors</hi> may cry out upon the <hi>Law: Traitors</hi> at the <hi>Prince:</hi> and <hi>Sinners</hi> againſt their <hi>God.</hi> But let us ſcan it ſeriouſly: And though you would miſchieveouſly inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, as though, our Governors ſhould have deſignedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived theſe, for ſo many Snares, and Gins upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Be informed my Brethren; for all they did was this. When other Rites were aboliſhed, they reſerved theſe, unabrogated. They made no Poſitive Act, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they did create, or Originally enact them; but only ſuffered them for to continue: and that, at a ſeaſon (as you ſhall hear anon) when no man ſcrupled, but all had uſed them. So far were they from a thought of Burdening Men's Conſciences thereby. And have we not now Reaſon to complaine, as Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> doth.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. to the Reader, before the Gov. of Chriſt's Church.</note> This is an endles Quarrel of theirs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring they either do not, or will not underſtand the matter, for which, we chiefly contend.</p>
            <p>But their <hi>Conformity</hi> would make them guilty of betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Liberty, wherewith Chriſt made them free. God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53540:7"/>that you ſhould be again intangled in the Yoke of Bondage,</hi> Gal. 5.1. But miſtake not Submiſsion unto Governors as inconſiſtent with your <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> To withdraw is <hi>Extravagancy:</hi> it is <hi>Licentiouſneſs,</hi> and not <hi>Liberty.</hi> That very <hi>uſeing of it for a Cloak of Maliciouſneſs,</hi> which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle reproveth, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> is an <hi>Exemption</hi> from the <hi>Jewiſh Paedagogy; a Manumiſsion from that Yoak, that our Fathers could not bear,</hi> Gal. 4.5. And beſide this, I know no <hi>Liberty</hi> appoſitely appropriated to the <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> for as it implies our <hi>Freedom</hi> from the <hi>Slava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Satan;</hi> it is <hi>Judaical,</hi> as much <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> A Branch of that <hi>Oath,</hi> which God ſware to <hi>Abraham, That we being delivered from the hands of our Enemies might ſerve him, in Holineſs, and Righteouſneſs all the days of our Life,</hi> Luk. 1.74.75. And ſo far is our Submitting unto <hi>Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> from treſpaſsing upon our <hi>Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> that each one of theſe, is an Inſtance of that <hi>Freedom,</hi> which, Chriſt purchaſed for us. For whereas it was the <hi>Jewiſh Yoke,</hi> that they were ſo determined in their Modes, and Forms, that they could not alter, nor diſpence with <hi>Proſelites,</hi> in ſuch <hi>Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> as with Men of diſſerent <hi>Climates,</hi> meet with as diverſe a Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Chriſt, to obviate that Infelicity, which, had been an unremoveable Impediment unto the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> hath whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delegated this Authority to the Pleaſure of his Church; requiring no more, <hi>then that all things be done Decently, and according to an Order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.40. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by a <hi>Canon,</hi> or <hi>Injuncton;</hi> for ſo the word, without the leaſt Impropriety of Signification, doth import: Whence they to whom this Language was Vulgar, term their Rules of Diſcipline, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, And ſo the Engliſh that follows <hi>Beza's Traſlation,</hi> renders the Text; <hi>Let all things be done Honeſtly, and By Order:</hi> which cannot but reſpect ſome Rule eſtabliſhed by Authority. So far is our <hi>Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> from Interfering with Authority, that whoſoever
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53540:7"/>extends it beyond theſe Limits, is no other than the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate of Confuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But their <hi>Conſcience</hi> will not ſuffer them to <hi>comply.</hi> I might churliſhly return, and with a ſting of <hi>Truth, What is that to us? See you to that.</hi> But, is it your <hi>Conſcience?</hi> Be not miſtaken. Perhaps, it is but ſome over-weeldy Opinion; or, if it be <hi>Conſcience,</hi> ſhew me the <hi>Rule,</hi> on which it doth proceed: for <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as your own Guides will tell you, doth not <hi>Accuſe,</hi> or <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,</hi> but according to ſome <hi>Rule,
<note place="margin">Jus. Div. Roy. Ecc.</note> Principle,</hi> or <hi>Law of God,</hi> that is above the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Now, the Work is ſhort; produce any thing above the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to juſtifie your Pretenſions, and we are ſilent for ever. But I would gladly ask, Did your <hi>Conſcience,</hi> of it ſelf, frame theſe <hi>Scruples;</hi> or, were they inſtill'd by <hi>Education, Converſe, Intereſt, Affection?</hi> &amp;c. If the former, is not your <hi>Conſcience defiled,</hi> and <hi>erronious?</hi> Tit. 1.15. For, if it be, you cannot expect, that out of <hi>Chriſtian Sympathy,</hi> we ſhould <hi>defile</hi> our ſelves, and <hi>err</hi> too. Beſides, ſome of your own <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve,
<note place="margin">Errans Conſcientia liganda, <hi>rather than</hi> ligat. <hi>Lightfoot's</hi> Ser. to <hi>Comm.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That ſuch a</hi> Conſcience <hi>is ſo far from binding, that it ought it ſelf the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be bound.</hi> If the latter, <hi>Wo be to them, by whom the Scandal cometh,</hi> Mat. 18.7. For this is that very Caſe, to which that <hi>Wo</hi> is threatned. The <hi>Scandal</hi> there, is not an averſion, or diſlike of ſomething that we ſee, is practiſed; but, the being enſnared thereby,
<note place="margin">Conſul. Ameſ. de Conſ.</note> into an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sin. Which is the miſery of our Diſſenting Brethren. If they Conform, they act againſt an <hi>Opining Conſcience,</hi> and they conclude that Sinful. If they refuſe, they become Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, in not ſubmitting to the <hi>Ordinance of Man, for the Lord's Sake,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. And how a <hi>Contracted Errour</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53540:8"/>ſhould excuſe our Non-performance of a <hi>Neceſſary Duty,</hi> is beyond my <hi>Divinity,</hi> to apprehend. In ſhort, if this <hi>Plea of Conſcience</hi> would juſtifie, there's not a <hi>Sect</hi> in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom,</hi> but hath a plauſible Evaſion. It remains there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that you get your <hi>Conſcience</hi> inform'd; and if you come with that Indifference which <hi>Epictetus</hi> requires in all that ſeek for <hi>Truth,</hi> even the ſame that is in <hi>Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> who matter not, whether their way be to the <hi>Right,</hi> or <hi>Left,</hi> or <hi>Forward,</hi> ſo that it leads them to their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-End. You have this Promiſe, <hi>That wherein you be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even that unto you,</hi> Phil. 3.15. But if the proſpect of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or <hi>Ambition,</hi> or ſuch By-Conſiderations, incline your <hi>Will,</hi> 'tis poſſible, from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that an Opinion might be true, you may believe it is true; your Well-wiſhes may overcome your Reaſon. For 'tis no ſuch uncouth thing, for <hi>Affection</hi> to advance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aſſurance;</hi> and the <hi>Paſſion</hi> for a <hi>Problem,</hi> to grow as ſtrong as Demonſtration; and then you are loſt for ever.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the common <hi>Topicks,</hi> which the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> uſe; how ſucceſsfully, I muſt refer to your own Judgment: only I obſerve, that our Diviſions do gradually advance; for as yet, they do but juſtifie themſelves, and apologize for their own Diſſentions. Let us take cognizance of their next <hi>Artifice,</hi> which is ſomewhat more <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian;</hi> for, when <hi>Arguments</hi> fail,</p>
            <p n="2">2. They endeavour to ſucceed, by creating <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> and conjuring up <hi>Suſpitions.</hi> A <hi>Fright</hi> may drive men paſt their Wits, and <hi>Dreams</hi> have more Influence on <hi>Superſtitious</hi> Souls, than the moſt <hi>Feeling Verities</hi> of Senſe and Reaſon. Juſt ſo it ſares with us; Men cry out of <hi>Popery, Popery, Pelagianiſm, Superſtition.</hi> For it is neither <hi>Miracle,</hi> nor <hi>Monſter</hi> with them, that a <hi>Church</hi>-man ſhould carry a <hi>Pope</hi> in his <hi>Belly.</hi> But, pray what do you mean by <hi>Popery?</hi> Nay, to this day, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53540:8"/>yet would tell us: and is it not a ſhrewd Suſpition, that there is no Truth in their meaning, when there is no Light in their Words; for, <hi>He that hateth the Light, is a doing Evil, and dare not come to the Light, leaſt his Deeds ſhould be reproved,</hi> Joh. 3.20.</p>
            <p>But where's the Danger, that you ſtorm ſo loudly? Have we Innovated in our <hi>Articles?</hi> Are our <hi>Homilies</hi> diſown'd? Or our <hi>Liturgy</hi> rejected? No, this would be joyful News unto the <hi>Brotherhood.</hi> But do not theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with <hi>Popery?</hi> As much as <hi>Light</hi> with <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> or <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Belial.</hi> And be awaked, my Brethren; Is it we, that refuſe to ſubſcribe the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Or, do we withdraw from the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> the <hi>Hanniball</hi> of <hi>Antichriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation?</hi> Where then is the <hi>Charity,</hi> to repreſent us ſuch <hi>Prostituted Wretches,</hi> as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue neither Promiſes, nor Proteſtations; Oaths nor Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions: whil'ſt others, that decline ſuch <hi>Teſts,</hi> as theſe, muſt paſs for <hi>Godly Men.</hi> Have we not Cauſe to ſpeak, when we cannot but hear a <hi>Celeuſma, Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry</hi> ſent after us, as <hi>Renegadoes</hi> of the <hi>Reformation?</hi> When we meet with <hi>Remonſtances</hi> of the <hi>Growth of Popery,</hi> one Part after another: as if nothing was wanting in our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union</hi> to that <hi>See,</hi> but only the Formality of a <hi>Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</hi> For God's Sake, remember, theſe groundleſs Fears brought one Prince to the <hi>Block</hi> (whoſe Innocent Blood is perhaps now viſited upon that Party; God in his juſt Judgment, upon their Impenitency, giving them up to return to their <hi>Old Treaſons,</hi> and in his Infinite Mercy towards our <hi>Loyalty,</hi> defeating their <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing their <hi>Rebellion</hi>) and, unleſs Men had deſigned to make the <hi>Son</hi> ſucceed his <hi>Father,</hi> to the <hi>Block,</hi> as well as <hi>Crown,</hi> they ſtand in Duty obliged, to check theſe falſe Surmiſes, to caſt out the <hi>Scorner,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Calumniator,</hi> that <hi>Contention</hi> may go out; yea, <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Reproach</hi> ceaſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.10. And I cannot but obſerve, that their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53540:9"/>againſt his late Majeſty, and the Clergy,
<note place="margin">By Andreas ab Haberfield.</note> was in that very <hi>Juncto,</hi> when a <hi>Plot</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> againſt his Sacred Perſon was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: an unanſwerable Sign, that they diſpaired of what the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> diſſembled, that they feared; his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination unto <hi>Popery.</hi> I dare ſcarce run the Parallel.</p>
            <p>Were the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Plotting againſt his Preſent Majeſty, an Evidence, what cool Affections he carried for their <hi>Superſtition?</hi> and can there be another Faction, that would obtrude themſelves into their Guilt, and wreſt the Infamy out of their hands! It troubles me to believe, there was.</p>
            <p>The ſame Decoy, the more <hi>Jealous Privilegioniſts,</hi> by dreading an Invaſion of their <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property.</hi> And though no Aſſurance is equal to Experience; not the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Solemn Declarations</hi> publiſhed, nor the Experience of more than twenty Years (in which, not ſo many <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Inadvertences</hi> have paſſed, as <hi>Violations</hi> of the <hi>Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi> been endured) is ſufficient to ballance the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited <hi>Omens</hi> of a <hi>Reſtleſs Faction.</hi> Indeed, amidſt that multitude of Buſineſs, which they that hold the Stern of Government, do manage, it is not poſſible, but Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences will happen; and there is not wanting Curſed <hi>Chams,</hi> who are pleaſed with the Diſcovery of their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Nakedneſs;</hi> Men, who improve and magnifie all their Miſtakes; and becauſe the <hi>Oracles</hi> have ſaid, That <hi>Magiſtrates are Gods,</hi> Pſal. 82.6. they will not ſuffer them for to ſlip as Men.</p>
            <p>Now, where lies the Chriſtianity of this Cenſorious Humour? <hi>Charity, that Bond of Peace,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>covers all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.7. Inclines men to conceal the Weakneſs of their Brethren; much more, of their Fathers; and is officious to hide a multitude of Sins, unſanctified <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that cries out, <hi>Humanum eſt errare,</hi> will become
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53540:9"/>their <hi>Advocate.</hi> And how can you, that are not without Sin your ſelves, dare to throw a Stone at the Head of Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Thus having calumniated both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deſinant tandem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledicere, ne malefacta exaudiant ſua.</hi> Ter.</note> they ſhew how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle they are pleaſed with the one, by the Coolneſs of their Affections to the other. For, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as at firſt, they did but juſtifie their ſelves, in not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing to the height of <hi>Conformity.</hi> Now they begin to gather into <hi>Conventicles,</hi> to hear <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and exerciſe a <hi>Diſcipline</hi> more <hi>Pure;</hi> that is, more <hi>Arbitrary</hi> (whence they are named <hi>Puritans</hi>) But neither as yet, do they forſake our <hi>Communion,</hi> but <hi>Halt betwixt</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Baal, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21. Preſs a neceſſity of Fellowſhip with us, though among themſelves, they afterwards (as a <hi>Bigot</hi> of their own, with as great Rudeneſs as Ignorance expreſſed it) would Serve God BETTER. Yet, they ſtop not here, <hi>The Water that hath got a Paſſage, ſpreads.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. They proceed to <hi>Burleſque,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fortiter calumniare &amp; aliquid adhaerebit.</note> and <hi>Libel.</hi> It is a ſure, but diviliſh <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, Fling Dirt enough, and ſome will ſtick.</hi> And how dutifully they have Scan'd this <hi>Directory:</hi> how diligently they have profited in this <hi>Science,</hi> examine with a little Patience, and you may be ſatisfied. From their firſt Appearance to this preſent Age, they never wanted a Succeſſion of Scurrility. There always have been Scorners that have fill'd the <hi>Chair,</hi> Pſal. 1.1. from <hi>Martin Marprelate,</hi> unto <hi>Andrew Marvel.</hi> Nor, was there Man, of what Eminence ſoever, that did appear againſt them, but under this Correction, from Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> down to Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet, Church</hi> and <hi>State, Prince</hi> and <hi>Prelate,</hi> have been wounded by theſe <hi>Arrows,</hi> their <hi>Bitter Words.</hi> It is an Accuſation that needs little Proof; the <hi>Proclamations</hi> of our <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Writings</hi> of our <hi>Biſhops,</hi> are full of theſe Complaints.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53540:10"/>With theſe Men 'tis nothing but a <hi>Rara Show,</hi> to <hi>Ridicule</hi> Soverainty; and by their Meaſures of <hi>Paying Reverence to the Lord's Anointed,</hi> one would be apt to gueſs, that under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> God had revers'd the <hi>Methods</hi> of <hi>Obedience,</hi> Acts 23.5. And commanded us only to ſpeak Evil of the Rulers of our People: <hi>Caeſars</hi> gracious Connivance, being grown to be a Priviledge of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<note place="margin">In Civitate libera mentem, &amp; linguam liberas eſſe debere.</note> no leſs than <hi>Parliament:</hi> all Men aſſuming as great Freedom to their Tongue as Thought. What Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, their Guides may give them, that I cannot tell: but never did I meet with a Divine of that <hi>Clann,</hi> that reprov'd this Vice; and what eſcapes without Correction, hath the Countenance of Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, or tacit Approbation. Yet, in pity, I ſhall tell them, what a Learned <hi>Prelate</hi> hath obſerved on this Piece of Prophaneneſs; <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>There were Times,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>when Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions were great in the</hi> Church, <hi>even to exceed Barbarity it ſelf.</hi> Did any Martyr, or Confeſſor in thoſe Times,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bp.</hi> Laud's <hi>Speech in Star Chamber.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Libel</hi> their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours? Surely, no, not one of them, to the beſt of my Remembrance. Yet theſe complain of <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> without all ſhew of Cauſe; and in the mean time, Libel and Rail without meaſure: ſo little akin are they to thoſe, who ſuffer for Chriſt, or the leaſt Part of Chriſtian Religion.</q> Nor is he alone in this his Judgment, for the Apoſtles be of the ſame Mind, who give this Character of <hi>Temporizing Chriſtians,</hi> That <hi>they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Dominion, &amp; ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> Ju. 8.9. 2 Pet. 2.10. A Policy ſo Suſpicious: the Bleſſed Angels feared to make uſe of it, when they truly might. For <hi>Michael the Arch-Angel durſt not bring againſt the very Devil</hi> (who queſtionleſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it) <hi>a Railing Accuſation;</hi> but meekly begg'd of God, that he would be pleaſed to <hi>rebuke him.</hi> And how his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53540:10"/>ſuits unto the Goſpel, which commands us, <hi>To pray for our Enemies, to bleſs them, which curſe us; when we are reviled, not to revile again; when we ſuffer, not to threaten;</hi> 1, Pet. 2.23. or how it doth tranſcribe our Saviours Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, who, <hi>as the Lamb was dumb before the Shearers, and opened not his mouth;</hi> is not my Province to enlarge upon. Only I concieve, it might be ſome Mitigation unto <hi>Davids Affliction,</hi> that they were <hi>Drunkards,</hi> that made <hi>Songs</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96.12. But that men, who are ſober, and conſcientious (if we may believe them) that they ſhould ſuffer either <hi>Head,</hi> or <hi>Hand;</hi> their <hi>Tounge,</hi> or <hi>Pen to touch the Lords Anointed, and do his Prophets Harm,</hi> Pſal. 105.15. is ſuch a Device of Religion, as I dare avouch the Goſpel is a Stranger to.</p>
            <p>But no Wonder, if their <hi>Proſelites</hi> forſake the <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of ſuch lewd men, as they Decypher us, and betake themſelves to ſome more powerful meanes. And this brings the Difference unto a <hi>Formal Schiſm.</hi> They depart from us, and ſet up <hi>Altar</hi> againſt <hi>Altar,</hi> and <hi>Pulpit</hi> againſt <hi>Pulpit; Doctrine</hi> againſt <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> againſt <hi>Worſhip.</hi> What is wanting to the <hi>Purity</hi> of their cauſe? they ſupply by the <hi>Impurity</hi> of their Lips, and impute the weakneſses of mens Perſons, to the Diſadvantage of their Principles. Like the <hi>Stoick</hi> in <hi>Lucian,</hi> who, reduced to a <hi>Non-plus,</hi> cries out <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, So they deal with us, <hi>Baſe words,</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> are an <hi>Ample Confutation.</hi> And when, by theſe Artifices, they have rendered the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment uneaſy, and the Governors odious.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They incite, and inſtigate unto Tumults by Turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Poſitions, and Seditious Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines. Such are theſe,
<note place="margin">See the Judgment of the Univ. of <hi>Oxf.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That Kings are but the Peoples Truſtees; That they are accountable for the Miſcarriages of the Government,</hi> with many more. And how directly theſe tend to <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi> I may be excus'd the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53540:11"/>For when a <hi>Prince</hi> is <hi>Dethroned</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> what can follow, but an <hi>Arbitrary Obedience.</hi> Subjection as long, and in what Inſtances they pleaſe; if he be the <hi>Peoples Creature,</hi> there needs no more to the full Proceſs of a <hi>Depoſition,</hi> then the <hi>Declaration; We will not have this man to reign over us,</hi> Luk. 19.14. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was aware of this, and therefore, requires you <hi>to be ſubject, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake,</hi> Rom. 13.5. Divinity they have no mind to be concerned with.</p>
            <p>What can now remain, but that the <hi>Populacy,</hi> thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd, in a tranſport of Zeal, <hi>do ariſe to deſtroy all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly that are in the Land; that they may root out the Evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from the City of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 101.11. <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Blood-ſhed</hi> and <hi>Murder, Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections</hi> and <hi>Rebellions</hi> are the <hi>End of theſe Diviſions.</hi> To this height hath the Quarrel about <hi>Modes</hi> and <hi>Habits, Geſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> riſen. Dear God! Is the life of man right, Dear in your Sight (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.15.) in their Eyes ſo cheap? Do we become obnoxious to <hi>Blood-ſhed,</hi> for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning a few <hi>Innocent Rites,</hi> and <hi>Primitive Ceremonies?</hi> All that I ſhall ſay, is this. The men that do theſe things, have either <hi>no Religion;</hi> or what is next to none, <hi>a Bad one.</hi> And what Temptation can you find in them, that you Careſs them as your Countreys Patriots.</p>
            <p>Were the late times of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> ſo pleaſant; that we ſhould be laborious to relapſe into the ſame? Survey the miſery; <hi>Fines, Confiſcations, Plunders,</hi> are but the <hi>Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Sorrows. Baniſhment, Impriſonment,</hi> and <hi>Death ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</hi> Or if you do ſurvive: What <hi>David</hi> of old Age may with more Dolefulneſs he affirm'd of that, <hi>your life can be but Labour and Sorrow,</hi> Pſal. 90.10. when your Perſon is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh'd, your Souls inſlav'd, your Churches prophan'd your Religion gone. God alone, who, foreſees all things, ſaw the Calamities that they were bringing on us, and in Mercy and Compaſſion, was pleaſed to prevent it.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53540:11"/>
            <p>Before I paſs this <hi>Topick,</hi> I muſt deſire you to remark, how they have aggravated their Opinions in the Cauſes of our Difference. What at firſt, were no worſe than <hi>Tolerabiles ineptiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calv. Ep. ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect.</note> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities that might be tolerated (the which was alſo ſpoken of <hi>Chriſm,</hi> and <hi>Extream Unction,</hi> Rites that are now diſuſed) are now grown to be <hi>Antichriſtian Impoſitions,</hi> and <hi>Prelatical Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</hi> Our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which ſome of the <hi>Fraternity</hi> did verily believe,
<note place="margin">FOX.</note> to be compoſed by the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> is now reproached as the <hi>Rags of Popery.</hi> Our <hi>Biſhops,</hi> whom <hi>Beza</hi> prays for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Succeſſion of;
<note place="margin">Bez. de div. grad. min. cont. Sar.</note> and the Repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of whom, was <hi>Corah's</hi> Sin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Aerius</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> are juſtled out with <hi>Ignominy,</hi> as <hi>Ithacian Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Perſecuting Prelates;</hi> as Men that hold the <hi>Stirrop</hi> for <hi>Popery</hi> to mount the <hi>Saddle.</hi> And our Kings, whom <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Artic.</hi> 37. <hi>Calv. in Am. c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> by a Miſtake of the meaning of that Title, which our <hi>Reformers</hi> gave them, <hi>The Supream Head of the</hi> Church, <hi>next under</hi> Chriſt, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining what is not dream't of; ſome <hi>Spirituality</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in it, did chance to cenſure: are look't upon, as either Enemies of, or Inconvenient to the Priviledges of the <hi>Kirk.</hi> Of which, you have an Inſtance in the <hi>Scotch Commiſſioners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Refor. of Ch. Gov. in Scot. by Com.</hi> pag. 10.</note> who taking notice of this <hi>Objection</hi> againſt the <hi>Presbyterial Government, That 'twas incompatible with Monarchy.</hi> Confeſs the <hi>Accuſation,</hi> in not pleading to it; or rather, reflect on the <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> by what they afterwards aſſert, <hi>That it is complyable with every Lawful Kind of Humane
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53540:12"/>Policy.</hi> Maliciouſly ſuggeſting, as if <hi>Monarchy</hi> was unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. You ſee, how the <hi>Floodgate</hi> being opened, the <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> do prevail, and <hi>Strife</hi> increaſeth.</p>
            <p>What our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> did at firſt with <hi>Modeſty,</hi> or by <hi>Miſtake,</hi> ſcruple, is now improved paſt all the hopes of Compoſition. The <hi>Pen</hi> is exchanged for the <hi>Sword;</hi> and a Combat of the <hi>Preſs,</hi> into a Battle of the <hi>Field.</hi> There is one thing behind, which as long as 'tis indulg'd, will both perpetuate our <hi>Difference,</hi> and amplify their Guilt: And that is,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Their <hi>Incredulity.</hi> They will believe no Evidence againſt their <hi>Affections:</hi> let it be written with the <hi>Beams</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> it is obſcure and dark to their <hi>Opticks.</hi> Theſe are Men, Gifted, either to deny the <hi>Truth,</hi> or extenuate the <hi>Fact.</hi> A few Inſtances of freſh Memory, may give you Satisfaction. The Murder of an <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> muſt by no means be imputed to the <hi>Bandying</hi> of the Party. And an <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> though he may have the Spirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Meaſure, cannot well be ſuppoſed to have Strength enough to be his own <hi>Executioner.</hi> Innocent Men! that cannot find Spots in their own Children, but admire their <hi>Blemiſhes</hi> for <hi>Perfections,</hi> and their <hi>Moles</hi> for <hi>Beauties.</hi> Men of a ſtrong <hi>Faith,</hi> that can believe their <hi>Plots</hi> the <hi>Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of their Enemies, and our <hi>Thankſgivings</hi> an <hi>Illuſion</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Heaven.</p>
            <p>Now, Perſons of this <hi>Obſtinacy,</hi> are irreclamable, and deſperate, paſt the ordinary Means of <hi>Recovery:</hi> what God may do, is not for us to reſolve. But methinks, they lie under a neceſſity of maintaining the <hi>Irreſiſtency</hi> of <hi>Grace:</hi> for that is all the Hopes they can have of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>Brethren,</hi> you accuſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> for this very Crime. <hi>Thou therefore that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? Or, art not thou inexcuſable, O Man! whoſoever
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53540:12"/>thou art, that Judgeſt; for wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf; for thou that Judgeſt, doſt the ſame things,</hi> Rom. 2.1. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> diſown the <hi>Tenets</hi> we alledge againſt them, becauſe they hear them not deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Sermons: and is not this your own <hi>Apology?</hi> Now, though we give a Reaſon for this Silence, That they be <hi>Doctrines,</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> Cannon is not to be applied to, for they may unadviſedly be preached out of Seaſon. Yet, are they not recorded in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. And the <hi>Pen</hi> leaves behind it, a more laſting Monument, and durable Character than that of the Tongue. And to do all men Juſtice, The <hi>Papiſt</hi> hath the more plauſible ground for Scruple; their <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> being for the moſt expreſſed in a <hi>Forreign Language;</hi> and the Liberty of the <hi>Preſs</hi> (as they pretend) denied un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their <hi>Advocates.</hi> Whereas theſe ingroſs the <hi>Preſs</hi> with their <hi>Seditious Pamphlets,</hi> and ſcatter the <hi>Poiſon</hi> in their <hi>Mother-Language.</hi> Not that I can excuſe either of them from the <hi>Phariſaical, Wilful,</hi> and <hi>Deſigned Calamity</hi> of thoſe, <hi>Who having Eyes, will not ſee; having Ears, will not hear; leaſt, ſeeking, they ſhould find, be converted, and healed,</hi> Mat. 13.15.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Incredulity</hi> of Men, ſided into <hi>Faction,</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much owing to the Nature of <hi>Contention;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nubibus atris Condita nullum Fundere poſſunt Sydera Lumen. Boet.</note> which darkens the <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> diſturbs the <hi>Judgment,</hi> and infatuates the <hi>Reaſon:</hi> though I dare not exclude the <hi>Immediate Hand of God;</hi> who, in a juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon their <hi>Unchriſtian Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> may perhaps have given them over unto a <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hate Mind.</hi> Rom. 1.28.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53540:13"/>
            <p>Theſe are the Conſequences of our <hi>Diſſentions,</hi> which, are the more to be lamented, in that othewiſe they ſeem to be Good Men; that have a <hi>Zeal</hi> of God, though not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Knowledge: Men that are kind to their Friends, and charitable to their Brethren. To whom, I may duly apply that of my Ld. <hi>Verulams,</hi> of another Sect, <hi>Tales cum ſint, utinam et noſtri eſſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this be the <hi>Condition</hi> of our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> (which I leave to God, and their own <hi>Conſcience</hi> to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, hoping they will be ſo juſt to their <hi>Souls Intereſt,</hi> to ponder it throughly) <hi>if this be their Condition?</hi> I muſt needs Query, If it be not time to lay aſide <hi>Animoſities,</hi> and leave off <hi>Contention,</hi> becauſe it hath been already too <hi>long meddled with?</hi> Which is the remaining Part of my Task. And to perſwade them to it; I ſhall return by the ſame Stages I advanced, and deſire them to conſider.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Heinouſneſs of thoſe Sins, in which theſe ſmall differences have engag'd them. Sins of no <hi>Lighter a Dye,</hi> then <hi>Maſſacres,</hi> and <hi>Murders, Inſurrections,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi> And what Sentence theſe muſt look for at the <hi>General Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes;</hi> allow them but the Benefit of their <hi>Clergy,</hi> and they may read, though not eſcape thereby. <hi>Rebellion</hi> is a Sin, no place whatever will endure, or connive at. Heaven caſt down the <hi>Rebellious Angels</hi> into <hi>Chains</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs: Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe</hi> baniſhed the <hi>Traitor Man,</hi> and keeps a Guard of <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi> and a <hi>Flaming-Sword</hi> againſt him. The very Earth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh'd, opens her mouth to demand Juſtice againſt <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> and <hi>his accurſed Accomplices.</hi> Nor dare Hell it ſelf pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Patroniſe an <hi>Inſurrection, For if Satan be divided againſt Satan, How ſhould his Kingdom ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this <hi>Sedition,</hi> which our <hi>Diſſentions,</hi> at preſent, have fomented, hath ſome Peculiarities in it, that do ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate the Guilt. For beſides the <hi>Hypocriſy</hi> of the Pretence, <hi>Religion;</hi> which, never meant to kill the Body, out of mercy to the Soul; nor murder Gods <hi>Image,</hi> to advance his Glory.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53540:13"/>
            <p>It was carried on with Deliberation, they meet, adviſe, debate, conſult; which ſpeaks their <hi>Fixedneſs</hi> and <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Had it been perpetrated in an Heat of Paſſion, the Exceſs would hove been ſome ſmall (though ſorry <hi>Apology</hi>) for ſo baſe a <hi>Villany.</hi> But their Deſign was to ſin with Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they ſcorn'd to be numbred amongſt the lower <hi>Claſs,</hi> of unwary, inadvertent Sinners, but will butcher Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberately, and in the Cool of their Blood. And is not this a hopeleſs, irrecoverable Temper? An Inſtance of a <hi>ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> (more than <hi>tender</hi>) Conſcience. This is what thoſe <hi>Divines</hi> make no mean Ingredient into the Sin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> For we cannot but imagine the Ingenuity of the Education, (which ſome glory in) could not but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them what <hi>Rebellion</hi> was: and the whole Party, who ſuppoſe the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be plain, clear, and full, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very Modes of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> cannot, ſurely miſconſtrue ſo Legible a Text, <hi>They that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation,</hi> Rom. 13.2.</p>
            <p>It was alſo againſt Signal Favours and Perſonal Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and <hi>Ingratitude</hi> is an <hi>Inhumane Sin.</hi> The very <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages</hi> are obliged by Kindneſs, and the <hi>Lyons</hi> of the <hi>Forreſt</hi> too generous to be undmindful of <hi>Beneficence.
<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſi dixeris, omnia dixeris.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> Lord <hi>Chanc. Eſſex,</hi> Ld. <hi>Lieut. of Irel. Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Pri. Coun. An hundred old Cap.</hi> Declar.</note> Yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe were Men that owed their Lives and Fortunes to his Majeſty's Clemency. And what a Barbarous <hi>Requital</hi> this? So <hi>Syrens</hi> charm the <hi>Ears</hi> that lend them Audience: ſo <hi>Vipers</hi> eat the <hi>Womb</hi> that gives them <hi>Being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Party will ſay, <hi>And what's all this to us? Are we reſponſible for other Men's Exceſſes? Muſt we be chargable for their Extravagancy?</hi> God forbid, that I ſhould believe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53540:14"/>all the <hi>Faction</hi> privy (much leſs conſenting) to ſuch horrid Villany; although the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy was very numerous.
<note place="margin">2000 in <hi>London Declaration.</hi>
               </note> Yet, my Brethren, it concerns you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, how ye may become Partakers of other Men's Sins. Had the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> taken Effect; which, (for ever praiſed be the Name of God) it did not. To whom would you have adhered? They preſumed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Aſſiſtance. And may we not ſuſpect, that Men of the ſame Communication, without the Spirit of <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy,</hi> may have an Inſight into each others Mind. We ſee how Birds of a <hi>Feather</hi> flock. And whil'ſt they obſerve you ſo eagerly to imbibe their <hi>Principles,</hi> credit their <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies,</hi> pleaſed with their <hi>Libels,</hi> is it poſſible that they ſhould believe, that you would ever boggle, or deſert their <hi>Intereſt.</hi> No, the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> which they were preparing, is an undeniable Argument of their Aſſurance. Would not you, (though exclaiming of the Treaſon) have protected and ſtrengthened the <hi>Regicides?</hi> Should we not have heard ſome old <hi>Maxim</hi> aſſum'd, to accomodate your <hi>Aſſociacions?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fieri non debet, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum valet.</note> And are not theſe Profeſſions of <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi> owing to ſuch a Conſideration, as to that of the <hi>Rebellious Iſraelites</hi> on their bad Succeſs: <hi>This</hi> Abſolom <hi>whom we</hi> Anointed <hi>over us, is dead in Battle; now therefore why ſpeak ye not a word of bringing back the King?</hi> 2 Sam. 19.10. I accuſe no one, by their own Conſcience let them ſtand or fall. But to diſmiſs this.</p>
            <p>As far as your <hi>Separation</hi> and <hi>Conventicles</hi> gave them In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement; as far as the Hopes of your Aid (though we ſhould favourably believe, they might have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in it) did animate and inſtigate them; ſo far muſt your <hi>Schiſm</hi> bear the Guilt of their <hi>Preſumption:</hi> and could you have the Impudence to wipe your mouth? you cannot truly ſay, <hi>You have done no Wickedneſs.</hi> The
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53540:14"/>moſt eaſie Conſtruction that can be fixed upon it, is, That in the Simplicity of your Souls; and knowing nothing, you ſhould have been inſnared into their Sedition, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. One would think, that the ſad Effect of ſuch ſpecious <hi>Pretexts</hi> in the late <hi>War,</hi> would make Men Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the ſame Events. For what a multitude was there, that would have laid down their Lives in exchange for his Majeſty, who being decoy'd into the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> by that ſame Artifice, are not able to waſh their Hands, and ſay with <hi>Pilate, I am Innocent of the Blood of this Juſt Perſon; See yee to it.</hi> Mat. 27.24.</p>
            <p>The Cauſe which hath inveigled you in ſo much Guilt, is ſmall, about things of little <hi>Moment,</hi> and meer <hi>Indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> and the <hi>Lightneſs</hi> of the Cauſe aggravates the <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the Sin. <hi>Moſes</hi> enquires, <hi>Why do ye Wrong one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, ſeeing that ye are Brethren,</hi> Act. 7.26. The near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Relation in his Opinion, being ſufficient to remove all the Grounds of <hi>Contention.</hi> What would he have ſaid, if it had not been a Matter of <hi>Wrong</hi> or <hi>Injustice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency,</hi> that they quarrelled about? They certainly have little Regard to the Peace of Chriſt's <hi>Church,</hi> that can diſturb it on ſuch ſmall Accounts.</p>
            <p>I know indeed, they deny the <hi>Indifferency</hi> of theſe Things: but a common Diſtinction would afford them <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> if they intended that, <hi>Viz.</hi> That in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they remain <hi>Indifferent,</hi> though not in the Uſe; for, being enjoyned, they become neceſſary unto <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The nature of <hi>Indifferency,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod neque contra Fidem, neque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra bonos Mores in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jungitur, Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renter eſt habendum.</note> St. <hi>Aug.</hi> his Rule will teach you, 'That which neither contradicts <hi>Faith</hi> nor <hi>Morality,</hi> is a thing <hi>Indifferent.</hi> And according to this Meaſure, we dare ſtand to your <hi>Verdict</hi> for the <hi>Indifferency</hi> of their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53540:15"/>Nature. But the neceſſity of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> the ſame <hi>Father</hi> doth impreſs from the Reſolution of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> which he Celebrated as the <hi>Reſponſe</hi> of an <hi>Oracle;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad quamcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam veneris,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry oft in his Writings.</hi>
               </note> which is, <q rend="inline">To conform your ſelves unto the <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of whatſoever <hi>Church</hi> you come to, whil'ſt they do not contradict the Rules of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality (i. e.)</hi> in things indifferent.</q> And agreeable to this, is the Derivation that ſome produce of the word <hi>Ceremony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Card. Bona. de reb. Lit.</note> from the <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Anathematize</hi> or <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate;</hi> as if we might infer, the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity</hi> thereto, to be a <hi>Guilt</hi> ſufficient to incur that Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>And that our Brethren may entertain more even thoughts, of theſe few, and eaſy (as they call them) <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</hi> I would intreat them to inſpect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Neceſſity of admitting <hi>Ceremonies</hi> to the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>There never yet' was that <hi>Religion</hi> in the World, that did appear without them, <hi>Judaical,</hi> as well as <hi>Heathen,</hi> in what it was diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Natural,</hi> was nothing elſe but a <hi>Syſtem</hi> of <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> although their <hi>Inſtitution</hi> was <hi>Divine.</hi> Whence St. <hi>Auguſt</hi> affirms poſitively, That there is no <hi>Religion</hi> whether true or falſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. L.</hi> 19. <hi>cont. Fauſt. C.</hi> 11.</note> that can ſubſiſt without <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</hi> And <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin</hi> as dogmatically (who being no <hi>Epiſcopal Divine,</hi> I hope may have your Ear) That the <hi>Church</hi> may;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Poteſt, ac debet Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiâ quaſdam Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monias instituere. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſ Cat. Q.</hi> 103. <hi>par.</hi> 3.</note> yes, and muſt inſtitute ſome <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</hi> And ſince men are taught by the Eye, as well as the Ear; and the more laſting Impreſſions iſſue thence. I would gladly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, why we may not be edified by the <hi>Geſtures</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> in ſome meaſures as well, as by the <hi>Labour</hi> of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53540:15"/>Lips. Or, why the Erection of my Perſon, may not adviſe the Beholders of the Elevation of the Mind, as much as if the <hi>Deacon</hi> did admoniſh them with his <hi>Surſum Corda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Happy is the Man that condemneth not himſelf in the Things that he alloweth,</hi> Rom. 14.22. For pray tell me, What are theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Ordinances</hi> paſſed and ordained by the Small and Great <hi>Councils</hi> of the the City of <hi>Geneva,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Laws of Geneva.</note> which the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> thereof promiſe, and ſwear to keep? Had they, for <hi>Ordinances,</hi> ſubſtituted <hi>Injunctions,</hi> or <hi>Cannons,</hi> which is all the ſame; the <hi>Church of England</hi> will be no more chargable with <hi>Impoſitions</hi> (unleſs the difference of words make the Grievance) than other <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> Why then ſuch Exclamations againſt her, when theſe are paſſed by in Silence? Or, how comes She to be more <hi>Prelatically</hi> than others, <hi>Presbyterially</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Examine the Reaſon why theſe <hi>Ceremonies</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Which, (after communicating therein with the Primitive Church) was a Motion of <hi>Charity,</hi> a Deſign thereby, to win upon the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> to give as little <hi>Scandal</hi> and <hi>Offence</hi> as poſſible. To convince them, that it was not <hi>Humour</hi> and <hi>Caprich,</hi> but <hi>Religion;</hi> not the Love of <hi>Innovation,</hi> but the Neceſſity of a <hi>Reformation,</hi> that made us withdraw: that it was not ſuch ſmall Things as <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> that we differed about (of which, this was an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that we enjoyned ſome) but Matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> and Articles of <hi>Salvation.</hi> We therefore are not aſhamed to own what ſome, with more Malice than Judgment, do retort, <hi>That our</hi> Liturgy <hi>is compoſed out of the</hi> Breviary <hi>and</hi> Miſſal. Is it Diſparagement to <hi>Gold,</hi> that it was mix'd with <hi>Lumber</hi> in the <hi>Oar?</hi> Is it <hi>Infamy</hi> unto <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Seat, that <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> did fill it? <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2. No, by this we ſatisfie the <hi>World,</hi> that we emov'd no further
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53540:16"/>from the <hi>Weſtern Patriarch,</hi> than he had wandred from his <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> and the <hi>Truth.</hi> And hereby the <hi>Church of England</hi> (and ſhe alone) gain'd ſuch an Aſcendant on the <hi>Papacy,</hi> as they never can be able to remove; who by communicating with us for ſeveral Years,
<note place="margin">In Q. Eliz. Reign.</note> plainly did confeſs the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a <hi>Reformation;</hi> and as high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend the Prudence of our <hi>Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I wiſh that our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren,</hi> would calmly remember, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were the only <hi>Faction,</hi> that at firſt were to be invited into our <hi>Communion.</hi> The Name of <hi>Puritan</hi> (unleſs amongſt thoſe of the <hi>Novatian Schiſm,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is no great Credit to the ambitious Title) was not ſo much as heard of, till After-Times, when Men had croſſed the <hi>Seas,</hi> and gone a Pilgimage unto <hi>Geneva,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hooper</hi> and <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heyl. Hiſt. Ref. Edw.</hi> 6.</note> they return'd infected with that <hi>Leaven,</hi> and ſet up for <hi>Goſpellers,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Puritans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What can be more charitable in this Caſe, than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede no further than was neceſſary? That we might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them, that our Proceedings were for the Honour of God, more than the Pleaſure of Man. <hi>Reformation</hi> hath only Reference unto <hi>Errour:</hi> ſo that what may be retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without <hi>Errour,</hi> cannot well be rejected without Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. On which ground 'twas thought convenient, in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, to omit that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> in the <hi>Rubrick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Common-Prayer.</note> concerning <hi>Kneeling at the Sacrament;</hi> that no Adoration was intended to it; (which both before and ſince, hath been inſerted) and you have heard how ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful it was. And the want of this Moderation, was no mean Obſtacle to the <hi>Reformation</hi> in our Neighbouring
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53540:16"/>Kingdoms. I know <hi>Calvin</hi> doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt it,
<note place="margin">Mediis Conciliis vel autorem eſſe vel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatorem. Calv. Ep. ad Prot.</note> and reproacheth it as an old Fault in <hi>Bucer.</hi> But though he might deſerve the Title of, Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, <hi>Bernardus non videt omnia.</hi> And it had been a happy Compoſition, if we could have won the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to have <hi>Reformed</hi> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of <hi>Faith,</hi> upon the Terms of admitting more <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials</hi> of <hi>Worſhip;</hi> which the <hi>Lutherans</hi> Adopt, and ſome <hi>Divines</hi> of Note were willing to comply with, in the Buſineſs of the <hi>Interim,</hi> which preſs'd a Reſtitution of the old <hi>Popiſh Ceremonies;</hi> whoſe Judgment was this, (which I intreat our Brethren to ruminate, for it deſerves to be written in Letters of <hi>Gold</hi>) <q rend="inline">That it is <hi>Lawful,</hi> yea, <hi>Neceſſary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. Conc. Trent.</hi> l. 3. an. 1548.</note> to tolerate ſome Servitude in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, when no <hi>Impiety</hi> is joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it.</q> And amongſt their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I find the Learned <hi>Melancthon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Burnet H. Ref.</hi> l. 2. an. 1648.</note> recorded by the Author of the late Hiſtory of the <hi>Reformation;</hi> whoſe Solid Judgment this doth ſeem to reliſh.</p>
            <p>This is the Reaſon of our retaining theſe <hi>Ceremonies:</hi> and ſince the Converſion of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> is as much, or more to be deſired (their Errours being greater, and their Guilt the deeper) deeper than the <hi>Diſſenting Proteſtants,</hi> that we ought to have an Eye as tender unto them, in the maintaining, as to the others in the abrogating of theſe <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> I dare with Confidence averr, our <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> themſelves being Judges; it is a <hi>Maxim</hi> delivered by their <hi>Leaders;</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That in things of this nature,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ref. of Ch. Gov. in Scot.</hi> p. 5.6.</note> when the Change is not to the better, it is both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and againſt Reaſon, to make a Change.</q> And I appeal to any ſober, moderate <hi>Diſſenter,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53540:17"/>if admitting a Change in theſe Things Indifferent, we could have ſo ſolid and plauſible an Argument to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon the <hi>Romaniſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us entreat you to enquire, by whom the <hi>Differen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that you ſo vigorouſly maintain, began: and when you ſee the Truth, we hope you may abate of the Heat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Extemporary Prayer,</hi> which you attribute to the <hi>Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox's and Forebr.</hi> Dr. <hi>Stillingf. Ep. to Hiſt. Sep.</hi>
               </note> was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice invented by a <hi>Wolf,</hi> that had got on <hi>Sheep</hi>'s Cloa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing, and practiſed by a <hi>Romiſh Prieſt</hi> in <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Weeds.</p>
            <p>Kneeling at the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> was traduc'd by <hi>John a Laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> from the <hi>Polonian Arrians,</hi> who robbing Chriſt of his <hi>Divinity,</hi> and believing him no more than <hi>Man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heyl. Hiſt. Ref. Edw.</hi> 6.</note> to expreſs the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality of their Natures, preſum'd to ſit with him at his Table.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Identity</hi> of the Orders of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and <hi>Presbytery,</hi> is a <hi>Novel</hi> of the <hi>School-Divines;</hi> who ſuppoſing it the higheſt <hi>Miniſterial Office</hi> (as if true, it muſt needs be) to make Chriſt a Body out of <hi>Bread;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conficere corpus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> unite the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> in one <hi>Order,</hi> whence both the <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian</hi> derive it.
<note place="margin">Conc. Trent.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Excluſion of the People, from bearing Part in the Worſhip of God, by their Suffrages and <hi>Voices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scrivener, Courſe of Divinity.</note> is an Injury which hath, prevailed ever ſince the Prayers were in an unknown Tongue; and for want of a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> is by them unreformed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sponſers</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and what is ſubſequent thereto, the Benefit of <hi>Confirmation</hi> comes to be neglected, after the Example of the <hi>Anabaptiſt.</hi> And <hi>Divines Presbytertal,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53540:17"/>as well as <hi>Prelatical,</hi> commend, though they do not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it.</p>
            <p>This is the true Riſe, and juſt Account of the things you ſcruple. <hi>Anabaptiſts, Arrians,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> were the men that broach'd them: and you, not barely <hi>Symbolize,</hi> but <hi>Communicate</hi> with them in Stickling for theſe. I dare not, as I ought, animadvert upon the looſneſs of theſe <hi>Contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Scruples,</hi> for fear I ſhould exaſperate your too <hi>Fiery Zeal.</hi> But in Charity, I muſt commend them to your <hi>Chriſtian Conſideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, I have touch'd the Wounds of our Friends, with as ſoft an hand, as the Affections, that I bear their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; or the Obligations, I have received from the Party, can in Juſtice expect from me.</p>
            <p>To conclude, You ſee how little <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> there is in the Methods you contrive for to foment the <hi>Difference.</hi> You muſt be anſwerable for thoſe <hi>Heart-Burnings,</hi> and <hi>Uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Jealouſies</hi> that you have of us: Thoſe <hi>Scurrilous Libels</hi> in which you do abuſe us: and thoſe <hi>Seditious Practices</hi> whereby you have unſettled us. If you can believe ſuch men as theſe to belong unto <hi>Chriſt's Flock,</hi> you have a <hi>Strange Faith.</hi> Or if you do not ſee, theſe things to be the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of ſuch men, you have a bad <hi>Eye-Sight,</hi> Gal. 5.20. <hi>Hatred, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ariance, Wrath, Strife, Sedition, Hereſies</hi> are catalogu'd with thoſe Works of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> that do <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude</hi> us from the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">And though you may retort, that <hi>Adultery, Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleaneſs, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Revellings</hi> (which I know not, by what kind of Propriety, are charged upon us, as the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land's Peculiars;</hi> when, Alas, they are too common to both Parties) ly under the ſame <hi>Condemnation.</hi> I believe your own <hi>Conſcience</hi> may be our <hi>Compurgatrix,</hi> that ſuch things paſs neither <hi>unreproved,</hi> nor <hi>unlamented.</hi> Or if thoſe, who value themſelves, as the more <hi>Sober Party,</hi> would be pleaſed by joyning our <hi>Communion</hi> to diſcourage
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53540:18"/>them by their <hi>Example.</hi> We would call upon them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce at your <hi>Converſion,</hi> and not ſtick to propoſe you for their <hi>Imitation.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider the <hi>Levity</hi> of theſe things that you diſpute, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the neceſſity of injoyning ſome <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and the Charity of retaining theſe. Inquire into the <hi>Original,</hi> and <hi>Growth</hi> of your <hi>Scruples;</hi> whence they came, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 'tis they tend, and as <hi>Abraham</hi> intreated <hi>Lot, Let there be no Difference, I pray thee, betwixt me and thee, for we be Brethren,</hi> Gen. 13.8. I know that you will offer an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, That both the Parties may move untill they meet. But Alas! my Brethren we are under the <hi>Law,</hi> and will you tempt us to diſobey? or becauſe you live without <hi>Law,</hi> will you invite us to tranſgreſs? This is ſuch a <hi>Strain</hi> of <hi>Impiety,</hi> as none but he that is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Tempter Exegetically,</hi> by your <hi>Officiouſneſs</hi> would ſeduce us to. And he that hath any Light of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> with <hi>Indignation</hi> muſt reject the Suggeſtion, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did St. <hi>Peters, Get thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me Siatan, for thou ſavoureſt not the things that be of God, but the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngs that be of men.</hi> Matt. 16.23. Nor is this an Expedient, if it were Practicable: for there may be a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in a Church, as well as from a Church. And ſhould we admit them, we might be juſtly cenſured, as <hi>Betrayers</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of that little <hi>Flock,</hi> that Chriſt hath yet miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly preſerved amongſt us: for whilſt one ſhould cry, <hi>I am of Paul, and another I am of Apollos,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.4. in the Cloſe, we all might come deſervedly to be reproved, as <hi>Carnal.</hi> But to ſatisfy our Brethren the Experiment hath been made,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heyl. 'Hiſt. Ref. Edw.</hi> 6.</note> that Party hath been benefited, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted in the Church: but were ſound ſo Turbulent, that Authority was conſtrain'd to <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and remove them.</p>
            <p>In Brief, Ponder the many wonderful <hi>Interpoſitions</hi> of the Almighty God, in the behalf of this diſtreſsed Church
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53540:18"/>and People. <hi>How oft have the ſnares been broken, and we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>vered,</hi> Pſal. 124.7. <hi>How hath the Lord turned again the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>vity of</hi> Sion, that our Enemies Confeſſion, <hi>The Lord hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one great things for them,</hi> hath put into our mouths the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hon, Yea the Lord hath donede great things for us, whereof we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ejoyce.</hi> Pſal. 126.2, 3. Providence is a <hi>Book,</hi> and though the Characters be ſo miſtical, that none but <hi>God</hi> can teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s how to read them; the Language often ſuch, that we muſt go to <hi>Heaven</hi> for to learn it. Yet where the <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence</hi> quadrates with the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> we may conclude, <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord hath ſpoken, and he hath fulfilled it.</hi> And when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ect on the Purity of our <hi>Doctrines,</hi> the Loyalty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaceableneſs of our <hi>Principles,</hi> I am ready to infer, 'He hath not beheld <hi>Iniquity</hi> in our <hi>Church,</hi> neither hath he ſeen <hi>Perverſneſs</hi> in our <hi>State:</hi> the Lord our God is with us, and the Shout of a King is amongſt us. Surely, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s no <hi>Inchantment</hi> againſt the <hi>Church;</hi> neither is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Divination</hi> againſt the <hi>State,</hi> According to this time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhall be ſaid of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State, What hath God wrought?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umb. 23. <hi>v.</hi> 21, 23.</p>
            <p>And let us pray God, that under the Shadow of his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings,</hi> we may ſtill continue a Monument of that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iſe</hi> which he hath made unto his <hi>Church, That the Gates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hell ſhall not prevail againſt Her,</hi> Mat. 16.18.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
